<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Markant Lab</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2020-10-24T09:47:39-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Doug Markant</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>VIS 2020 [paper] - Belief updating from scatterplots</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/VIS/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/VIS</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do people change their beliefs when they see a data visualization like a scatterplot? Communicating science and making evidence-based arguments often involve data visualizations like the one below. It can be tempting to think that “the data speaks for itself”—that it paints a clear, relatively unambiguous picture about the relationship between a set of variables. But the mere presentation of statistical evidence, no matter how strong, does not guarantee that people will change their minds, particularly when they have strong preexisting beliefs that run counter to the data.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;//assets/mask_data.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mask use&quot; width=&quot;350px&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A recent figure showing a strong negative correlation between mask-wearing and COVID19 case counts. Would this change someone's mind if they believe these variables are unrelated?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.00058&quot;&gt;VIS 2020 paper&lt;/a&gt;, my colleagues and I examined how people update their beliefs about statistical relationships when viewing scatterplots. We developed some new methods for eliciting beliefs about these relationships and used computational modeling to evaluate the impact of data visualizations on belief updating. The project adds to a growing number of studies that aim to better understand (and model) how people learn through interactive data visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A favorite paper of mine which reviews the many ways people &lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt; updating their beliefs in the face of contradictory evidence is &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.3102/00346543063001001?casa_token=jfRYOu5D1FAAAAAA:k6XnFHj-1QPV-SqcC9pFKob3iI5j-QIewkgoUPlO6qOeEosoScL20lRW7LmO6X_WIT-vhpMzYpjQtg&quot;&gt;Chinn and Brewer (1993)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CogSci 2020 [talk] - Chained study and relational discovery</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/24/cogscitalk/"/>
   <updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/24/cogscitalk</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How do people discover relational knowledge through experience? I recently presented a talk on this topic at the all-virtual &lt;a href=&quot;https://cognitivesciencesociety.org/cogsci-2020/&quot;&gt;2020 Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society&lt;/a&gt;. See the embedded video below for an overview of the project, or the &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Markant_CogSci2020_TIAwareness.pdf&quot;&gt;proceedings paper&lt;/a&gt; for more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://widgets.figshare.com/articles/12743354/embed?show_title=1&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CogSci 2020 [poster] - Risk preferences and option generation</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/22/cogsciposter/"/>
   <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/22/cogsciposter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s well-known in the behavioral sciences that people differ in their attitude toward taking risks. Some individuals are risk-seekers who like to roll the dice, while others are risk-averse because they prefer to play it safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past studies of risk attitudes have typically focused on &lt;em&gt;well-defined&lt;/em&gt; choices in which the set of possible actions are predetermined by the researcher and the possible outcomes of each action are known. For example, a person might face a choice between:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option A (safe): earning $5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option B (risky): earning a lottery ticket with a 5% chance of winning $100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual’s risk preference is thought to influence whether they will go with the safe or risky option in this kind of well-defined decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But many real-world choices are &lt;em&gt;ill-defined&lt;/em&gt;, in that a set of choice options is never explicitly provided to you. Instead, you have to generate possible courses of action for yourself. Do risk preferences affect how people &lt;em&gt;generate&lt;/em&gt; actions in ill-defined, uncertain situations, just as they affect choices between predetermined options?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the question behind an ongoing project in the lab (with Meagan Padro and Mitra Mostafavi) and the topic of a poster that will be presented at CogSci 2020. To learn more, click on the image below to get the PDF of the poster. If you attend CogSci swing by the (virtual) poster session on August 1, 11:00-12:40 EDT!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2020_CogSci_poster.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020_CogSci_poster.png&quot; alt=&quot;cogsci-poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Psychonomics 2018 - Building relational knowledge through active control</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/17/psychonomicsposter/"/>
   <updated>2018-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/17/psychonomicsposter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In some prior work, my colleagues and I have found that active control—being able to dictate the content or pacing of information—leads to enhanced episodic memory for materials experienced during study.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Let’s say that I’m your instructor and I have a set of definitions on flashcards that I want you to learn. If I give you (the student) more control over the selection and pacing of flashcards, it’s likely that you’ll have better memory later on compared to conditions where you don’t have control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as an instructor, I don’t &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; want my students to memorize a set of independent definitions. I also want them to integrate those concepts together to form some coherent knowledge about the domain. For example, I don’t just want my research methods students to be able to define different types of validity; I also want them to be able to relate them to each other and the broader goals of experimental methods. In contrast to the first goal of forming memories of independent sets of items, it is less clear to what extent having control over learning leads to enhanced integration of study experiences into conceptual knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project described in this poster aims to understand the effects of active control on relational knowledge formation. It uses a common relational reasoning task (transitive inference) to disentangle enhancements to memory for individual items from enhanced &lt;em&gt;integrative encoding&lt;/em&gt;. The results so far suggest that having control over the selection of items leads to improved integrative encoding over a passive condition lacking such control. Critically, however, the benefit of active control only appears among people with higher working memory capacity. This provides another piece of evidence that the benefits of “active learning” may not be so universal, but instead depend on students having the cognitive resources to maintain and integrate disparate study experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the image below to get the PDF of the poster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2018_Psychonomics_poster.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2018_Psychonomics_poster.png&quot; alt=&quot;psychonomics-poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Markant, D., Ruggeri, A., Gureckis, T. M., and Xu, F. (2016). &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/MarkantEtAl_MBE2016.pdf&quot;&gt;“Enhanced memory as a common effect of active learning.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;Mind, Brain, and Education.&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Markant, D., Dubrow, S., Davachi, L., and Gureckis, T.M. (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/s13421-014-0435-9&quot;&gt;“Deconstructing the effect of self-directed study on episodic memory.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;Memory &amp;amp; Cognition 42&lt;/i&gt;(8), 1211—1224. doi: 10.3758/s13421-014-0435-9 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Psychonomics 2016 - Adaptive exploration in decisions from experience</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/15/psychonomicsposter/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/15/psychonomicsposter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you’re on Amazon trying to decide which of two products to purchase. One way to learn about the options before you buy is to look at reviews from other people who have bought the same items. Each review gives you a glimpse into the relative value of each option, and you can explore each item (i.e., keep on reading reviews) for as long as you like until you feel ready to hit the buy button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how many reviews do you decide to read for each product? How does the variability in the ratings affect how long you explore—for example, is there a difference between seeing a string of solid 4-star reviews as opposed to a mixture of 5-star and 3-star reviews? How does your exploration change when searching for a relatively mundane product like a power adapter as opposed to a major purchase like a computer?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Psychonomics this week I’m presenting some new results from a project where we try to understand how people adapt their exploration in response to these kinds of environmental factors, including the variability in the outcomes they experience and the rewards that are at stake. The experiment described in the poster below was designed to test the predictions of a sequential sampling model that accounts for this adaptive exploration and its effects on how people make choices. Sequential sampling models are widely used to model the relationship between choices and response times in a number of decision making tasks&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and our results suggest that similar mechanisms can account for the way that people sample experiences from the environment prior to making a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the image below to get the PDF of the poster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2016_Psychonomics_poster.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2016_Psychonomics_poster.png&quot; alt=&quot;psychonomics-poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m using product reviews as an illustrative example of experience-based decision making in the wild (our experiment was more stripped down), but some recent research has looked exactly at how sampling review ratings to learn about products impacts choice (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/bdm.1841/full&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See this recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.psychonomic.org/news/316843/When-EZ-does-it-Simpler-models-are-sometimes-better-than-their-complex-cousins.htm&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; for a nice introduction to sequential sampling models as applied to choice RT. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CogSci 2016 - Hypothesis generation and self-directed learning</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/08/16/cogsciposter/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/08/16/cogsciposter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At CogSci this year I presented some new work on hypothesis generation and its role in self-directed learning (specifically, the learning of categorical rules). This project explores the idea that hypothesis generation is a bottleneck in active learning, as is suggested by a lot of work in classic cognitive tasks as well as studies from educational psychology. The results give an example of how biases in the hypothesis generation process can have a big impact on whether people can efficiently learn different kinds of rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more on this project, see the &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Markant_CogSci2016.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in the proceedings and the poster below (&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2016_CogSci_poster.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2016_CogSci_poster.png&quot; alt=&quot;cogsci-poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Enhanced memory as a common effect of active learning (new paper)</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/07/13/mbe/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/07/13/mbe</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/mbe.12117/abstract&quot;&gt;new paper out in Mind, Brain, and Education&lt;/a&gt;, coauthored with Azzu Ruggeri, Todd Gureckis, and Fei Xu. In the paper we argue that one reason active learning improves outcomes relative to passive conditions (like lectures) is that exercising control leads to enhanced memory (in particular, episodic memory for the events experienced during learning).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many lab-based tasks, having control over learning (e.g., controlling the selection or pacing of new information) often leads to better memory compared to yoked conditions in which such control is absent but the same information is experienced. By surveying a range of research that has employed this kind of active/yoked design in different domains, we outline how improved memory can arise from a number of different mechanisms depending on the kind of control afforded to the active learner. Thinking about real-world learning activities in terms of this basic dimension of control (which is just one part of what people typically think of as “active learning”) may help us understand when and why active learning tends to produce better outcomes than traditional instruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of things struck me while researching the paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some form of episodic memory is important to many theories of conceptual learning or semantic memory – but episodic memory is not really a focus in educational research. Perhaps unsurprisingly, educational psychologists seem to be primarily interested in measures of conceptual learning: does the student remember the definition of a term, or how to solve a certain kind of physics problem? As far as I can tell there isn’t much work examining memory for the details of the learning experience (e.g., the activities completed, example problems that were encountered, conversations during class, etc.) and how it relates to other performance measures.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a similar gap in lab-based research related to inquiry-based learning (including work on category and causal learning which usually shows an advantage for active control over yoked observation). This work has largely focused on the value of the information that active learners select (e.g., do they ask questions that are useful? Can they come up with experiments that lead to unconfounded evidence?). But it seems likely that the same set of memory-based mechanisms could play a role, particularly in real-world inquiry learning settings that involve richer materials and forms of interaction than the typical lab-based experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing the paper helped me pinpoint some of these big open questions about how memory and control interact during learning. Of course, despite our best efforts it’s inevitable that we missed some existing work that would be useful. If you know of something relevant or have any other comments about the paper, let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Active learning workshop at CogSci</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/07/04/cogsciworkshop/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/07/04/cogsciworkshop</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Next month I’ll be participating in a full-day workshop at CogSci,
entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/activelearningworkshop16/home&quot;&gt;“Active learning: Cognitive development, education, and 
computational models.”&lt;/a&gt;
The workshop will feature lots of terrific researchers from the CogSci community 
who have been thinking about active learning from many angles.
Come by if you are in Philly on Wednesday!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
